We learned in מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin that if a man sends
a גט Get through a שליח, Shliach, the שליח Shliach must say
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. Bifnei Nichtav U'Bifnei Nechtam. This ensures the גט
Get is valid. The גמרא Gemara explains the reasons for
this, whether it is because we need to confirm
the signatures or because we need to ensure the
writing of the גט Get was done לשמה, Lishmah, for the
sake of the specific woman. This illustrates a vital
יסוד Yesod in הלכה Halacha regarding the trust we place in
a שליח. Shliach. Whenever we perform a מצוה, Mitzvah, we must
ensure it is done with the right כוונה. Kavanah. Even
though we are in גלות, Galus, our עבודה Avodah is to
refine ourselves and the world around us until we
merit the גאולה Geulah with the coming of משיח, Mashiach, במהרה
בימינו, Bimeherah Beyameinu, אמן. Amen. Another point to mention is that if
you just leave the ice in the cup and
it melts on its own, that is not a
problem of מוליד molid because you are not doing an
active מעשה. ma'aseh. It's happening ממילא, mimeila, on its own. So,
you can put ice in your drink, but don't
crush it. The משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah clarifies in סעיף קטן
ל"ה Seif Katan Lamed Hey that the liquid is מתבטל misbatel into
the water already present. Next, the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch discusses
in סימן ש"כ Siman Shin Chaf סעיף י' Seif Yud what happens
with snow on your clothes. The מחבר Mechaber says, היה
שלג על בגדיו מנערן, Hayah sheleg al begadav menaran, if there is
snow on his garments, he may shake them. This
is because snow isn't נבלע, nivla, it's not absorbed. Therefore,
there's no איסור issur of מלבן. melaben. However, the רמ"א Ramah notes
we should be מחמיר machmir if it's not a great
צורך. tzorech. Also, we are told that walking on snow
is מותר. muttar. The גמרא Gemara explains that since the crushing
is incidental, it's not the מלאכה melacha of ריסוק. risuk. It's
just the normal דרך derech of walking, so it's permitted
on שבת. Shabbos. In this week's פרשה, parsha, פרשת תרומה, Parshat Terumah,
we find the first instruction for building the משכן.
Mishkan. The תורה Torah says, ויקחו לי תרומה מאת כל
איש אשר ידבנו לבו תקחו את תרומתי. Vayikchu li terumah me'eis kol
ish asher yidvenu libo tikchu es terumasi. Take for
me an offering from every man whose heart motivates
him, you shall take my offering. The word תרומה,
terumah, usually translated as contribution or offering, comes from
the root word רום, rom, meaning to lift up. When
a person gives with a full heart, they are
not just giving an object; they are elevating themselves
and the object. The רמב"ן Ramban explains that the main
purpose of the משכן Mishkan was to be a place
where the שכינה, Shechinah, the divine presence, could rest among
the בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. And how is that achieved? Through
אשר ידבנו לבו, asher yidvenu libo, through the willingness of the heart.
Later on, when describing the כרובים Keruvim on top of
the ארון, Aron, the תורה Torah says their faces were איש
אל אחיו, ish el achiv, one towards the other. רש"י Rashi notes
that this happened when בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael were doing the
will of השם. Hashem. When they weren't, the כרובים Keruvim turned
away. It all depends on the heart. If the
heart is involved, if there is a true נדיבות
לב, nedivus lev, a generosity of spirit, then the physical building
becomes a home for the שכינה. Shechinah. We should all
merit to give from the heart and create a
place for השם Hashem in our lives. This is the
path of perfect תשובה: Teshuva: to take every part of
our personality and bring it back to its source,
back to הקדוש ברוך הוא. HaKadosh Baruch Hu. And similarly with the
trait of עזות, Azut, boldness. A person should not be
impudent with people, but he should have עזות דקדושה,
Azut DKedushah, holy boldness, to stand up for the
truth and not be embarrassed before those who mock
him in his service of השם. Hashem. Every trait, even
the ones that seem negative, has a root in
the divine. The work of a person is to
elevate these traits and use them according to the
will of the בורא, Borei, the Creator. This is what
it means to serve השם Hashem with both of your
יצרים, Yetzarim, your inclinations, both the יצר הטוב Yetzer Hatov and the
יצר הרע. Yetzer Hara. When we take the energy of the
יצר הרע Yetzer Hara and channel it into our passion for
תורה Torah and מצוות, Mitzvot, we are performing the highest level
of עבודה. Avodah. This is why the holy ספרים Sefarim tell
us that a person who has a very strong
יצר, Yetzer, a strong drive, has the potential to reach
much higher levels than someone who is naturally quiet
and passive. The more fire a person has inside,
the more he can ignite his soul to burn
with a love for אלקות, Elokut, for Godliness. But if
he doesn't work on his מידות, Middos, that same fire
will consume him with negative desires and anger. Therefore,
the study of מוסר Mussar and the work of refining
our character is the foundation of everything. Without it,
even our holy actions can be tainted by our
own ego. May we all merit to find the
path of balance and to use every part of
ourselves to bring גילוי שכינה, Giluy Shechinah, the revelation of the
Divine Presence, into this world. Now we can extend
this concept to other areas of life as well.
The משנה Mishnah in מסכת שקלים, Masechet Shekalim, פרק ג משנה ב,
Perek Gimmel Mishnah Bet, discusses the process of תרומת
הלשכה, trumas halishkah, which was taking the money from the chamber
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to buy the קרבנות ציבור,
korbanos tzibbur, the communal sacrifices. The משנה Mishnah says that
the person who went in to take the money,
to take the coins out of the boxes, he
was not allowed to wear a garment that had
sleeves where he could hide money, and he wasn't
allowed to wear shoes or sandals or תפילין tefillin or
a קמיע, kameia, an amulet, because if he would become
rich afterwards, people might say that he took the
money from the לשכה, lishkah, from the chamber, and hid
it in his clothes or in his shoes. And
the משנה Mishnah concludes with the same phrase: לפי שאדם
צריך לצאת ידי הבריות כדרך שצריך לצאת ידי המקום,
lefi she'adam tzarich latzeis yedei habriyos k'derech shetzarich latzeis
yedei HaMakom, because a person must satisfy the requirements
of people just as he must satisfy the requirements
of the Omnipresent. This is based on the פסוק
pasuk that we mentioned: והייתם נקיים מה׳ ומישראל. v'heyitem nekiyim me'Hashem u'mi'Yisrael.
We see from here a very fundamental principle. It's
not enough for a person to know in his
own heart that he's doing the right thing. It's
not enough to say, "I know I'm honest, Hashem knows I'm honest,
and I don't care what people think." Of course, when it comes
to performing מצוות, mitzvos, we shouldn't be affected by people who mock
us. As the רמ״א Rema says in the very first סימן siman
in שולחן ערוך: Shulchan Aruch: ולא יתבייש מפני בני אדם המלעיגים עליו,
v'lo yisbayesh mipnei bnei adam hamal'igim alav, a person shouldn't be embarrassed
in front of people who mock him for his service of Hashem.
However, when it comes to matters of integrity, when it comes to
money and honesty, then we have a responsibility to make sure that
we are above suspicion. We have to act in a way that
even a person who is looking to find fault won't be able
to find any. This applies to anyone who holds a public position,
anyone who deals with money that belongs to others, whether it's a
גבאי צדקה, gabbai tzedakah, a treasurer of a שול shul or an
organization, or even a person in business. We have to be extra
careful to make sure that everything is transparent and that there's no
room for any misunderstanding. This is part of the concept of קידוש
השם, kiddush Hashem, of sanctifying the name of Heaven. When people see
a religious person, a שומר תורה ומצוות, shomer Torah u'mitzvos, acting with
the highest levels of integrity and being careful to avoid even the
slightest appearance of impropriety, that brings great כבוד, kavod, great honor, to
Hashem and to the תורה. Torah. On the other hand, if a
person is careless and acts in a way that causes people to
suspect him, even if he's actually innocent, it can lead to a
חילול השם, chillul Hashem, a desecration of the name of Heaven. Therefore,
we must always have this principle in front of our eyes: והייתם
נקיים מה׳ ומישראל. v'heyitem nekiyim me'Hashem u'mi'Yisrael. We should always strive to
be clean and pure in our relationship with Hashem and in our
relationships with our fellow human beings. Now we learned in the משנה
Mishnah in the beginning of מסכת ברכות, Masechet Berachot, "מאימתי קוראין את
שמע בערבית". Me’eimatai korin et shema be’arvit. From what time do we
read the שמע Shema in the evening? "משעה שהכהנים נכנסים לאכול בתרומתן".
Mishe’ah shehakohanim nichnasim le’echol bitrumatan. From the time that the כהנים Kohanim
go in to eat their תרומה. Terumah. The גמרא Gemara asks over
there, "תנא היכא קאי דקתני מאימתי". Tana heicha ka’i dekatani me’eimatai. Where
did the תנא Tana stand before this that he’s now asking "from
when"? The גמרא Gemara answers that he’s coming from the פסוק pasuk
of "בשכבך ובקומך". Beshachbecha uv-kumecha. The תורה Torah tells us to say
שמע Shema when we lie down and when we get up. So
now the משנה Mishnah asks, "from when" is the time of lying
down? This is the fundamental starting point of שס, Shas, of the
whole תלמוד בבלי. Talmud Bavli. We start with the timing of a
מצוה. mitzvah. נשמת כל חי Nishmat Kol Chai also carries this same
light and this same power. The text of נשמת Nishmat is made
up of words that can be found in the ברכת המזון. Birchat
HaMazon. And it's for this reason that many of the חסידישע Chasidishe
ספרים Sefarim tell us that saying נשמת Nishmat is a סגולה Segulah
for פרנסה. Parnassah. Just as ברכת המזון Birchat HaMazon is a blessing
for sustenance, נשמת Nishmat is a blessing for the soul. And when
we thank השם Hashem with the words of נשמת, Nishmat, we are
tapping into that same flow of abundance. The נשמת Nishmat prayer is
called the ברכה Bracha of the song, the ברכת השיר. Birchat HaShir.
It is the ultimate expression of gratitude. It reminds us that every
breath we take is a gift from the Almighty. כל הנשמה תהלל
יה, Kol HaNeshamah TeHallel Yah, every soul shall praise God. When we
say נשמת כל חי, Nishmat Kol Chai, we are acknowledging that our
very life force comes from Him. This connection between נשמת Nishmat and
ברכת המזון Birchat HaMazon shows us that our physical needs and our
spiritual essence are one. We shouldn't separate them. Everything comes from the
same source. May we always merit to say these words with a
full heart and realize the miracles that surround us every single day.
We are in מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin דף מ"ד עמוד א'. Daf
Mem Dalet Amud Aleph. We learned in the משנה: Mishna: המוכר עבדו
לעכו"ם יצא לחרות. hamocher avdo la'akum yatza lecheirut. If a person sells
his slave to a non-Jew, he goes free. This is a קנס,
knas, a penalty that the חכמים Chachamim imposed on the owner because
he's causing the slave to lose out on his מצוות. mitzvos. The
גמרא Gemara asks over here: what is the דין din if he
sells his slave only for a certain amount of time? Let's say
he sells him for thirty days. And the גמרא Gemara brings a
מחלוקת machloket between רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and the חכמים. Chachamim. רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says that even if you sell him only for
one day, יצא לחרות, yatza lecheirut, he goes free. Why? Because you're
already making him lose out on the מצוות. mitzvos. Now, it's interesting,
the גמרא Gemara says that the owner can't just say, "I'll take
him back." Once he's sold, the בית דין Beis Din forces the
owner to buy him back from the non-Jew, even for a high
price, and then he goes free. This is to ensure that a
person is careful not to sell his slave to someone who will
cause him to stop keeping תורה ומצוות. Torah u'mitzvos. ואינו יכול להוציאו.
Ve'eino yachol lehotzio. And he's not able to take him out. אמר
אביי. Amar Abaye. תניא כוותיה דאביי. Tanya kavatei d'Abaye. המוכר עבדו לעובד
כוכבים. Hamocher avdo l'oved kochavim. If a person sells his slave to
a non-Jew, יצא לחרות, Yatza lecheirut, he goes free, וצריך לכתוב לו
גט שחרור, V'tzarich lichtov lo get shichrur, and he has to write
for him a bill of manumission, ומאחריו, Umacharav, and from the master.
אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. במה דברים
אמורים? Bameh devarim amurim? When are these things said? שלא כתב עליו
אונו. Shelo katav alav ono. When he didn't write for him a
bill of sale. אבל כתב עליו אונו, Aval katav alav ono, but
if he did write a bill of sale for him, זה הוא
שחרורו, Zeh hu shichruro, that is his manumission. המוכר עבדו לעובד כוכבים.
Hamocher avdo l'oved kochavim. When a person sells his slave to a
non-Jew, פוסלו מלאכול בתרומה. Poslo meloechol b'terumah. He invalidates him from eating
תרומה. Terumah. Even though technically he's still a slave and if he
was a כהן's Kohen slave he could eat תרומה, Terumah, once he's
sold to a non-Jew, he can no longer eat תרומה. Terumah. ואם
היה רבו כהן, Ve'im hayah rabbo Kohen, if his master was a
כהן, Kohen, מאכילו בתרומה, Ma'achilo b'terumah, he could eat תרומה, Terumah, he's
now disqualified. אמר רבי יוסי. Amar Rebbi Yosei. בדא. Bada. In this
case, לא אמרו יצא לחרות, Lo amru yatza lecheirut, they didn't say
he goes free, אלא שיכתוב לו רבו שחרור, Ela sheyichtov lo rabbo
shichrur, unless his master writes him a manumission, ויאמר לו, Veyomar lo,
and he says to him, הרי אתה בן חורין, Harei atah ben
chorin, you are now a free person. Now the גמרא Gemara goes
on. הדרן עלך המוכר עבדו. Hadran alach hamocher avdo. We have finished
the פרק Perek of המוכר עבדו. Hamocher Avdo. Now we're starting a
new פרק, Perek, פרק Perek number five, פרק הניזקין. Perek Hanizakin. הניזקין,
Hanizakin, damages. שמין להם בעידית. Shamin lahem b'idit. When we evaluate damages,
we pay from the best quality land, ובעל חוב בבינונית, Uva'al chov
b'veinonit, and a creditor is paid from medium quality land, וכתובת אשה
בזיבורית, Uchtuvas ishah b'ziburis, and a woman's marriage contract is paid from
the poorest quality land. רבי מאיר אומר, Rebbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says, אף כתובת אשה בבינונית, Af chtuvas ishah b'veinonit, even
a woman's marriage contract is paid from medium quality land. Now the
משנה Mishna continues with several laws that were instituted מפני תיקון העולם,
Mipnei tikkun ha'olam, for the sake of the betterment of the world.
אין נפרעין מנכסים משועבדים. Ein nifrahin minechasim meshubadim. We don't collect from
property that has been sold במקום שיש נכסים בני חורין, Bimkom sheyesh
nechasim b'nei chorin, in a place where there are free properties. Even
if the free property is of poor quality, if the creditor wants
to collect, he has to collect from the free property first, אלא
אם כן היו זיבורית, Ela im kein hayu ziburis, unless they were
of the poorest quality. אין נפרעין מנכסי יתומים. Ein nifrahin minechasei yetomim.
We don't collect from the property of orphans, אלא מן הזיבורית, Ela
min haziburis, except from the poorest quality property. Now
the משנה Mishna says: המביא גט ממדינת הים. Hamavi get mimedinas hayam.
A person who brings a גט Get from overseas. If
he can't say it was written in my presence
and signed in my presence because the husband died,
the משנה Mishna says we cannot collect from the property.
Now the משנה Mishna continues with more laws of תיקון
העולם. Tikkun ha'olam. המוצא מציאה. Hamotzei metziah. One who finds a lost
object, לא ישבע מפני תיקון העולם, Lo yishava mipnei tikkun ha'olam, he
does not have to swear for the sake of
the betterment of the world. If a person claims
that he found a certain amount and the owner
says you found more, normally he would have to
swear. But חכמים Chachamim said he doesn't have to swear,
otherwise people won't want to return lost objects. Now
the גמרא Gemara begins. השתא. Hashta. Now. לגבות מבינונית אמרת, Ligvos mibeinonit
amart, you said we collect from medium quality land,
מזיבורית מיבעיא, Miziburis miba'aya, is it necessary to say from poor
quality? If we're allowed to collect from medium land,
obviously we can collect from poor land. The גמרא
Gemara answers: הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. This is what the משנה
Mishna meant. אין נפרעין מנכסים משועבדים. Ein nifrahin minechasim meshubadim. We don't
collect from sold property במקום שיש בני חורין, Bimkom sheyesh b'nei chorin,
in a place where there are free properties, ואפילו
הן זיבורית, Ve'afillu hen ziburis, even if the free properties are poor
quality. If the debt was supposed to be paid
from עידית, Idit, the best land, or בינונית, Beinonit, medium land,
and the debtor sold his best land but kept
his poor land, the creditor has to take the
poor land from the debtor rather than going to
the לוקח, Lokeach, the person who bought the better land.
Now the גמרא Gemara asks: what is the reason for
this? Why did חכמים Chachamim say that we don't go
to the לוקח, Lokeach, the purchaser, if there's בני חורין?
B'nei chorin? מפני תיקון העולם, Mipnei tikkun ha'olam, for the sake of
the betterment of the world. Because if a person
knows that his property can be seized even if
there's other property available, no one will want to
buy land. People need to have security when they
purchase property. If there is בני חורין, B'nei chorin, free property,
the creditor must go there first. Then the משנה
Mishna said: אין נפרעין מנכסי יתומים אלא מן הזיבורית.
Ein nifrahin minechasei yetomim ela min haziburis. We don't
collect from orphans' property except from the poorest land.
The גמרא Gemara asks: what is the reason for this?
Why are orphans treated differently? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbi Yochanan, משום
חינא, Mishum china, because of grace. Meaning, we want people to
be willing to lend money to orphans or to
deal with them, but we also want to protect
the orphans' interests so they don't lose their best
land. Another reason given is that orphans don't know
the business dealings of their father, and therefore we
give them the benefit of the doubt and only
allow collection from the poorest land. This is all
part of תיקון העולם. Tikkun ha'olam. Why is this night different
from all other nights? שבכל הלילות אנו אוכלין חמץ
ומצה הלילה הזה כולו מצה. Shebechol haleilos anu ochlin chometz umatzah halaila
hazeh kulo matzah. On all other nights we eat
chametz and matzah; on this night only matzah. שבכל
הלילות אנו אוכלין שאר ירקות הלילה הזה מרור. Shebechol haleilos anu ochlin
shear yerakos halaila hazeh maror. On all other nights
we eat other vegetables; on this night maror. שבכל
הלילות אנו אוכלין בשר צלי שלוק ומבושל הלילה הזה
כולו צלי. Shebechol haleilos anu ochlin basar tzali shaluk umvushal halaila hazeh
kulo tzali. On all other nights we eat meat
roasted, boiled or cooked; on this night only roasted.
שבכל הלילות אנו מטבילין פעם אחת הלילה הזה שתי
פעמים. Shebechol haleilos anu matbilin paam achas halaila hazeh shtei peamim. On
all other nights we dip once; on this night
twice. שבכל הלילות אנו אוכלין בין יושבין ובין מסובין
הלילה הזה כולנו מסובין. Shebechol haleilos anu ochlin bein yoshvin uvein msubin
halaila hazeh kulanu msubin. On all other nights we
eat either sitting or reclining; on this night we
all recline. Now the רמבם Rambam notes that the version
of מה נשתנה Ma nishtana differs slightly based on whether it
was בזמן הבית bizman habayis or בזמן הזה. bazman hazeh. For example,
the question about the roasted meat was only said
בזמן הבית. bizman habayis. And then he says, "We were slaves
to Pharaoh in Egypt," and he completes the entire
הגדה. Haggadah. Anyone who adds and elaborates on the story
of what happened to the Jewish people is praiseworthy.
And then he recites the sections explaining the significance
of the פסח, Pesach, the מצה, matzah, and the מרור. maror. The
פסח Pesach is because the Almighty passed over the houses
of our ancestors in Egypt. The מרור maror is because
the Egyptians embittered the lives of our ancestors in
Egypt. The מצה matzah is because they were redeemed. And
these things are all commanded by the תורה. Torah. And
in every generation a person is obligated to see
himself as if he himself had just now gone
out from the slavery of Egypt. Therefore we are
obligated to thank, to praise, to glorify and to
extol the One who performed all these miracles for
our ancestors and for us. He then begins the
הלל. Hallel. He recites until the end of the second
chapter, ending with the words חלמיש למעינו מים. chalamish l'maino mayim. And
then he recites the ברכה, beracha, אשר גאלנו, Asher Ge'alanu, "Who has
redeemed us and redeemed our ancestors from Egypt," and
he concludes, "Blessed are You Hashem, גאל ישראל, Ga'al Yisrael, Who has
redeemed Israel." And then he drinks the second cup while reclining on
his left side. הלכה ב. Halacha Beis. After that he recites the
ברכה, beracha, המוציא לחם מן הארץ, Hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz, on the
whole מצה matzah and then on the broken piece he says the
ברכה beracha of על אכילת מצה. al achilas matzah. And then he
takes a כזית kezayit from the whole one and a כזית kezayit
from the broken one and eats them. And then he recites the
ברכה, beracha, על אכילת מרור, al achilas maror, and he dips the
מרור maror in the חרוסת charoses and eats it. He should not
leave it in the חרוסת charoses for a long time so that
the taste of the מרור maror is not nullified. Then he wraps
the מצה matzah and the מרור maror together and he dips them
in the חרוסת charoses and eats them without a ברכה. beracha. הלכה
ג. Halacha Gimel. Afterwards he eats his meal, eating whatever he wants
to eat and drinking whatever he wants to drink. At the end
of the meal he eats of the meat of the פסח, Pesach,
at least a כזית, kezayit, and he doesn't eat anything after it.
בזמן הזה, Bazman hazeh, in our times, he eats a כזית kezayit
of מצה matzah and he doesn't eat anything after it so that
the taste of the מצה matzah or the taste of the meat
of the פסח Pesach remains in his mouth. הלכה ד. Halacha Dalid.
Afterwards he recites the ברכת המזון Birkas HaMazon on the third cup
and he drinks it. And then they pour the fourth cup and
he completes the הלל Hallel and says the ברכת השיר, Birkas Hashir,
which is the ברכה beracha of יהללוך ה' אלוקינו. Yehalelucha Hashem Elokeinu.
And then he recites the ברכה beracha on the fourth cup and
he doesn't drink anything after it. Coming back to the בית המדרש
beis hamedrash and finding your לימוד limud and your סדר seder and
your place within it. Whether you're doing an עמוד amud of גמרא
gemara or a דף daf or you're learning things בעיון, b'iyun, the
point is to make a קנין. kinyan. And when we think about
what a קנין kinyan is, we think about שטר, shtar, כסף, kessef,
we think about all these things. But the most important part of
a קנין kinyan is that I own it, that I understand it,
to have a ביאור biyur on every single word that you're saying.
דוד המלך David HaMelech would say, אני מעורר השחר, Ani Me'orer Hashachar,
I wake up the dawn, ואין השחר מעורר אותי, Ve'ein Hashachar Me'orer
Osi, and the dawn does not wake me. The גמרא Gemara asks:
what was the difference between משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu and דוד המלך?
David HaMelech? Why did משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu say כחצות, KeChatzos, about
midnight, whereas דוד המלך David HaMelech knew exactly when חצות Chatzos was?
The גמרא Gemara answers that משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu knew exactly when
חצות Chatzos was. Why did he say כחצות? KeChatzos? Because he was
afraid that the אצטגניני פרעה, Itztagninei Paroh, the
astrologers
of
פרעה,
Paroh,
would
make
a
mistake
and
say
that
משה
Moshe
is
a
בדאי,
Badai,
that
he
is
a
liar.
However,
דוד
המלך
David
HaMelech
had
the
כינור.
Kinnor.
The
כינור
Kinnor
told
him
exactly
when
חצות
Chatzos
was.
Therefore,
דוד
המלך
David
HaMelech
was
able
to
wake
up
at
exactly
חצות
Chatzos
and
learn
תורה
Torah
until
the
morning.